Guide to the Meredith Tax papers, 1956-2016 RL.01275
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Organizational Materials, 1958-2013; 130 boxes
  - Women's Liberation: Biblio., Address lists, Courses, Women's Studies (Box 111)
  - Women's Liberation: Clippings misc. (Box 111)
  - Clippings (Box 111)
  - Affirmative Action (Box 111)
  - Misc papers current (Box 112)
  - Women's history group, 1969-1970 (Box 112)
  - Women's Liberation: Boston-NY: Female liberation, 1969 (4 folders) (Box 112)
  - Women and Women's Liberation movement, my notes and papers, 1971-1972 (Box 112)
  - Women's Liberation: CP (Box 112)
  - Women's studies group (Conference, school, etc), 1971-1972 (Box 112)
  - Women's Liberation: ILGWU Conference, 1971 (Box 112)
  - Working Women questionnaires (Box 112)
  - Women's Liberation: Articles (Box 112)
  - Clippings on Women's Movement (Box 112)
  - Women's Liberation: Toronto Conference (Box 113)
  - Anti Imperialism (Box 113)
  - Chicana (Box 113)
  - Childcare (Box 113)
  - England (Box 113)
  - Europe/World (Box 113)
  - ERA (2 folders) (Box 113)
  - Gay women's movement (Box 113)
  - Prostitution (Box 113)
  - Quebec (Box 113)
  - Rape (Box 113)
  - SDS documents (Box 113)
  - New Haven (Box 113)
  - Midwest (Box 113)
  - New Left: Song books and scores (5 folders) (Box 114)
  - RNC, 1972-1973 (Box 115)
  - ACWL, 1972 (Box 115)
  - Trotskyism, 1972-1975 (Box 115)
  - Economist groups, 1971 (Box 115)
  - Sojourner Truth, 1972-1974 (Box 115)
  - MLS, 1978-1988 (Box 115)
  - PUL, 1970-1980 (Box 115)
  - Black Workers Congress, 1973-1975 (Box 115)
  - CL, 1972 (Box 115)
  - P.R.: YLP and MPI, 1972-1974 (Box 115)
  - Notebook, London, 1967 (Box 115)
  - Stop It Committee, 1968 (Box 115)
  - Stop It Committee, 1967 (Box 116)
  - Evidence, London, 1966-1967 (2 folders) (Box 116)
  - Anti-War Movement, US (Box 116)
  - BPP (Box 116)
  - Black Movement, late 60s and early 70s (Box 116)
  - New Left - Boston (Box 116)
  - New Left- Theory (Box 116)
  - England (Box 117)
  - Japan (Box 117)
  - Quebec (2 folders) (Box 117)
  - North America News Service, 1972 (Box 117)
  - Students (2 folders) (Box 117)
  - Weathermen/Other Terrorists (Box 117)
  - Prairie Fire re: Women (Box 117)
  - Workers Control (Box 117)
  - B'Nai Jeshurun (Box 118)
  - Brit Tzedek, 2002 (6 folders) (Box 118)
  - Gila Suirsky (Box 118)
  - Lectures re: Israel, 2001 (Box 118)
  - WW Israel-Palestine Project (Box 118)
  - Sumaya Farhad-Naser (Box 118)
  - Daphna Golon, mss (Box 118)
  - Clippings (Box 118)
  - NYC Junity/Women in black, 2001 (Box 118)
  - Americans for Peace Now (Box 118)
  - NIMN-NY Org. efforts (Box 118)
  - JUNITY Conference, Chicago, 2001 (Box 118)
  - Jews/Is real Peace work (3 folders) (Box 118)
  - JUNITY Conference position papers (Box 119)
  - News From Within, Vol. XVII, no. 1 and 2 (Box 119)
  - Dr. Ana Ashrawi (Box 119)
  - Censorship in Palestine (Box 119)
  - Jeff Halper, Israeli Committee vs. House Demolition (Box 119)
  - Israeli Press (Box 119)
  - New Profile (Israel) (Box 119)
  - Oslo Peace Process Analysis (Box 119)
  - Right of return (Box 119)
  - Ed Said (Box 119)
  - Arthur Waskow (Box 119)
  - Brit: Max and Anna Levinson Fdn (Box 119)
  - Rita and Stanley Kaplan (Box 119)
  - Patricia Golan (Box 119)
  - European Jews - Diaspora, 2003 (Box 119)
  - Israel (Box 119)
  - Press lists, 2002 (Box 119)
  - APN (Box 119)
  - Avnery Tour, 2001 (Box 119)
  - JFREJ (Box 119)
  - NYCA anti-occupation (Box 119)
  - Haggai Matar tour, 2002 (Box 119)
  - JFREJ (Box 119)
  - NY Chapter fundraising and money, 2003 (Box 119)
  - Habonim Dror (Box 119)
  - JFREJ (Box 119)
  - Brit Tzedek chapter, 2002 (Box 119)
  - Brit Brochure, NYC (Box 119)
  - Jews/Israel Peacework (2 folders) (Box 119)
  - Brit Tzedek, 2002 (Box 120)
  - Hersh Smolar (Box 121)
  - Soviet Jews (Box 121)
  - American Jews (Box 121)
  - Jews and Feminism (Box 121)
  - Israel in the 80s, Conflicts (Box 121)
  - Jews/Israel Peace work (2 folders) (Box 121)
  - Articles (Box 122)
  - Ads re: Israel (Box 122)
  - Clippings (3 folders) (Box 122)
  - Newsday series on Israel, 1988 (Box 122)
  - American Friends of Peace Now (Box 122)
  - Peace Now - American Friends of, 1982-1987 (Box 122)
  - New Israel Fund (Box 122)
  - New Jewish Agenda - Manhattan Chapter, 1983-1988 (3 folders) (Box 122)
  - Interviews - re: Jews, Israel (Box 122)
  - Peace Now (and Friends of), 1987-1988 (Box 122)
  - API - Americans for Progressive Israel (Box 122)
  - New Israel Fund and other "dialogue" and "non-political" groups (Box 122)
  - Coalitions: Inter denominational (Box 122)
  - New Outlook: Al Fajr Conference, 1988 (Box 122)
  - Passover Peace Demo, 1989 (Box 123)
  - Guggenheim application, 2002 (Box 123)
  - NYPL Center for Writers and Scholars Fellowship, 2002 (Box 123)
  - Jews/Israel Peace work (2 folders) (Box 123)
  - National Writer's Union (Box 124)
  - West Side Community School and son Eli's schoolwork, 1990-1995 (Box 125-127)
  - New Feminist Library, 1980-1985 (Box 127a)
  - National Writers Union, 1982-1987 (Box 127a)
- Writings, Speeches and Songs, 1956-2016; 65 boxes
  This series contains materials related to Tax's writings, speeches and songs. It includes drafts and research files from her historical novels Rivington St. and Union Square (working title The Bright Future) about Eastern European immigrants living in New York City in the early twentieth century and their engagement with radical politics. There is some material about Tax's 1980 book The Rising of the Women, about rise of feminism and its relationship with union and labor movements, and its 2001 reprint, as well as some material about her 1980 children's book Families. Articles and columns she wrote for a number of publications, including The Nation, are included. It also includes drafts of an unpublished novel and memoir, professional correspondence related to her writing career, as well as early writings and memorabilia from high school and college.
  - Incomes Tax, ca. 1960 (Box 128)
  - High School writings and memorabilia, ca. 1956-1960 (Box 128)
  - High school memorabilia, 1959 (Box 128)
  - College notes and memorabilia, 1960-1962 (Box 128)
  - Theater memorabilia, 1958-1960 (Box 128)
  - Notebook with scripts and songs, 1956-1961 (Box 128)
  - High school essays, 1958 (Box 129)
  - College notes and memorabilia, 1962-1963 (Box 129)
  - Undergraduate class notes, circa 1960-1964 (Box 196)
  - Writings and memorabilia, 1958-1960 (Box 130)
  - Scrapbook, 1954-1959 (Box 131)
  - Scrapbook, 1956-1959 (Box 132)
  - College Thesis notecards, ca. 1963-1964 (Box 133)
  - Slavery/kid's book, ca. 1981 (Box 134)
  - Bibliographies, 1969-1975 (Box 134)
  - Encyclopedia of the New Left, 1987 (Box 134)
  - Literary Anthology, 1988 (Box 134)
  - New Statesman competition, 1965 (Box 134)
  - Thesis typescript, London, 1968 (2 folders) (Box 134)
  - Notebook, 1989 (Box 134)
  - Research, 1979 (Box 135)
  - Monthly Review, 1980 (Box 135)
  - Correspondence, 1978 (Box 135)
  - Women Rising, 1980-1981 (2 folders) (Box 135)
  - Speeches, 1991 (Box 135)
  - Correspondence, 1990 (Box 135)
  - Correspondence, 1982-1983 (3 folders) (Box 136)
  - Readings, 1980 (Box 136)
  - Book notes, 1986 (Box 136)
  - Book notes, undated (2 folders) (Box 137)
  - Rising of the Women royalties, 1990 (Box 137)
  - Union Square royalties, 1988 (Box 137)
  - Finances, 1982 (Box 137)
  - Rivington St. finances, 1982 (Box 137)
  - Families, 1986 (Box 137)
  - Out of Egypt proposal, 1991 (Box 137)
  - Memoir, 1989 (3 folders) (Box 138)
  - Family Misery, 1991 (Box 138)
  - Proposals, 1989 (2 folders) (Box 138)
  - Growing Spurts, undated (Box 138)
  - Friends proposal, 1990 (Box 138)
  - Rivington St. notebooks, drafts and rewrites, 1979-1981 (Box 139-142)
  - Rivington St. typescript draft, 1981 (Box 143-145)
  - Union Square notes and drafts, 1984-1987 (Box 146-154)
  - Union Square drafts, undated (2 folders) (Box 155)
  - Union Square publicity, 1988-1990 (10 folders) (Box 155)
  - Union Square draft, 1985 (4 folders) (Box 156)
  - Union Square publicity, 1988-1990 (6 folders) (Box 156)
  - Rising of the Women, 1980 (Box 157)
  - Rising of the Women, 1970-1979 (Box 209)
  - Across the Lines (3 folders) (Box 158)
  - The Life You Save, 1990 (3 folders) (Box 158)
  - The Life You Save, 1990 (Box 159)
  - Speeches, 1977-1978 (3 folders) (Box 160)
  - Research files, 1968-1977 (8 folders) (Box 160)
  - Woman and Her Mind pamphlet, 1970 (Box 160)
  - Writings, 1970-1971 (Box 160)
  - Song, There Was an Old Woman, 1977 (Box 160)
  - Songbooks, notes and outlines, 1970-1971 (Box 160)
  - Song correspondence, 1969-1970 (Box 160)
  - Speeches and articles, 1978-1983 (Box 161)
  - Speeches and articles, 1983-1985 (Box 162)
  - Speeches and articles, 1985-1986 (Box 163)
  - Speeches and articles, 1987-2002 (Box 164)
  - Speeches and articles, 1989-2002 (Box 165)
  - Speeches and articles, 1993-1999 (Box 166)
  - Speeches and articles, 1997-2009 (Box 167)
  - Speeches and articles, 1990-2006 (13 folders) (Box 168)
  - Memoir draft, undated (Box 168)
  - Memoir draft, 1993 (2 folders) (Box 169)
  - Book proposal, 1992 (Box 169)
  - Notes, 1990 (Box 169)
  - Miriam drafts, 2001-2001 (2 folders) (Box 169)
  - Authors' Guild, 2000 (Box 170)
  - The Rising of the Women, 2001 reprint (4 folders) (Box 170)
  - Readings and appearances, 2001-2002 (Box 170)
  - Articles, 1990-2010 (Box 171)
  - Writings, publicity and press, 1991-2004 (Box 172)
  - Writings, 1995-2005 (Box 173)
  - Grants and fellowships, 1980-1991 (Box 174)
  - Writings, 1977 (Box 174)
  - Women Writers' Group, 1979 (Box 175)
  - Notes on other writers' works, 1974-1980 (Box 175)
  - Columbia Seminar Paper, 1984 (Box 175)
  - Rethinking Marxism handouts, 1988 (Box 175)
  - Book project, 1988 (Box 175)
  - Crux, 1987 (Box 175)
  - Feminists and feminism, undated (Box 176)
  - Elizabeth Gurley Flynn, 1970 (Box 176)
  - Gompers autobiography, undated (Box 176)
  - Garment industry research, circa 1978-1980 (9 folders) (Box 176)
  - Socialist Party research, circa 1978-1980 (Box 177)
  - Women and labor research files, circa 1978-1980 (Box 178-182)
  - Soviet Jews research files, circa 1978-1980 (Box 183-185)
  - Women labor activists research files, circa 1978-1980 (Box 186)
  - Communist Party research, circa 1978-1980 (Box 187)
  - Revolting Behavior: New Paltz conference scandal (Box 209)
  - Fashion Plates: Union Square drawings by Tax (Box 209)
  - Union Square publicity binder (Box 209)
  - Reviews of Tax's books and related clippings (Box 210-211)
- Correspondence, 1959-2006; 9 boxes
  This series contains Tax's correspondence. Personal and professional correspondence are intermixed.
  - Correspondence, 1968-1994 (Box 188)
  - Correspondence, 1978-1992 (Box 189)
  - Correspondence, 1979-1989 (Box 190)
  - Correspondence, 1976-1989 (Box 191)
  - Correspondence, 1978-1991 (Box 192)
  - Correspondence, 1959-1965 (Box 193)
  - Correspondence, 1962-1991 (Box 194)
  - Correspondence, 1986-1992 (Box 195)
- Subject Files, 1960-2001; 8 boxes
  This series contains files complied by Tax during the course of her research. Relates to topics she addressed both as part of activist organizations and as a writer, as well as a file on the censorship of her children's book Families.
  - Africa/U.S., 1960-1973 (Box 197)
  - Asia, 1972 (Box 197)
  - Albania, 1971 (Box 197)
  - Angola, 1976 (Box 197)
  - Asian-Americans, 1972-1974 (Box 197)
  - Brazil, 1963 (Box 197)
  - Chicanos, 1970 (Box 197)
  - Chicanos in Chicago, 1973 (Box 197)
  - Chile, 1972 (Box 197)
  - Cuba, 1972 (Box 197)
  - Cultural War NYC, 1972 (Box 197)
  - Cultural work/workers, 1972 (Box 197)
  - Detroit, 1970 (Box 197)
  - El Salvador, 1980 (Box 197)
  - Eastern Europe, 1973 (Box 197)
  - Europe, 1973 (Box 197)
  - Health, 1969-1973 (Box 197)
  - Hospitals, 1972 (Box 197)
  - India, 1972 (Box 197)
  - Indians (U.S.), 1973 (Box 197)
  - International, 1972 (Box 197)
  - Ireland, 1971 (Box 198)
  - International Socialism, 1971 (Box 198)
  - Labor Committee, 1968 (Box 198)
  - Latin America, 1973 (Box 198)
  - Left, 1977-1979 (Box 198)
  - Mexico, 1973 (Box 198)
  - Middle East, 1972-1974 (Box 198)
  - New Working Class, 1971 (Box 198)
  - New University Conference, 1969 (Box 198)
  - Philippines, 1973 (Box 198)
  - Prison movement, 1974 (Box 198)
  - Puerto Rico, 1972 (Box 199)
  - Repression, 1978 (Box 199)
  - Radical Education, 1968-1969 (Box 199)
  - Schools, 1971 (Box 199)
  - Social services, 1973 (Box 199)
  - Unions, 1973 (Box 199)
  - Workers, 1970 (Box 199)
  - Black Movement, 1968-1972 (Box 199)
  - Black Panthers, 1970-1972 (Box 199)
  - Sisterhood is Global, 1995-1999 (Box 199)
  - Women's International Coalition for Economic Justice (WICEJ), 2001 (Box 199)
  - Clippings, re: women, 1977 (Box 200)
  - Houston Women's Convention, 1977 (Box 200)
  - Women's Groups New York, 1977 (2 folders) (Box 200)
  - NARAL, 1977-1980 (Box 201)
  - Abortion, 1969-1989 (7 folders) (Box 201)
  - Abortion, birth control, v.d., 1970 (Box 201)
  - National Women's Health Network, 1978-1979 (Box 201)
  - Our Bodies, Ourselves, 1977-1990 (Box 202)
  - Collection of 68 political and activist-themed buttons, undated (Box 202)
  - U.S. Censorship (4 folders), 1994-1997 (Box 203)
  - Feminists for Free Expression, 1995 (Box 203)
  - Human Rights, 1995 (Box 203)
  - National Coalition Against Censorship, 1993-1997 (Box 203)
  - Censorship and Education, 1992-1996 (Box 203)
  - Families, censorship of, 1994-1999 (3 folders) (Box 203)
  - Education reform, 1994-1995 (2 folders) (Box 203)
  - People for the American Way, 1993-1994 (Box 203)
  - Sex Ed, 1994-1995 (Box 203)
  - Articles on women (2 binders), 1935-1938 (Box 209)
- Audiovisual Series, 1971-2003; 5 boxes
  Conditions Governing Access note
  Original audiovisual materials are closed to patron use. Research Services staff need to produce use copies of some materials before contents can be accessed. Use copies of the audiocassettes in Boxes 205-207 available on reading room workstation.
  - VHS tapes and discs
    - 3.5 inch discs, 1986-1994, 39 (Box 204)
    - 4 VHS tapes, Conversation with a Refusenik, Interview with Meredith Tax interview with Svetlana Alexievitch, and a panel discussion featuring Meredith Tax, 1992-2003 (Box 208)
  - Audiocassettes
    89 audiocassettes, 53 of which contain research interviews and 36 of which contain interviews with Tax, readings by Tax and board meetings, 1971-1997
    - Int. Martha Schaeffer 1-64, First Tape (Box 205)
    - Audiocassettes (Box 206)
    - Audiocassettes (Box 207)
- Printed Materials
  Scope and Contents
  Pamphlets and periodicals from Tax's library; some foreign language materials
  - Pamphlets and periodicals from Tax's library (Box 1-4 (Acc. 10/196))
- Accession (2017-0173), 1962-2016
  - Centre for Secular Space (CSS) Launch Strategy, 2011-10-17 (Box 212)
  - CSS Notes, Meetings, 2011 (Box 212)
  - "Double Bind" annotated draft, 2013 (Box 212)
  - Open Letter from CSS to NYRblog's Human Rights Watch, 2012-04 (Box 212)
  - "Cageprisoners" annotated article, 2011 (Box 212)
  - CSS Files: Palestinian/Blasphemy, 2013 (Box 212)
  - CSS Files: Reem Abdel-Razek asylum, 2013 (Box 212)
  - CSS Files: Jane Gahmel Open D, 2013-07 (Box 212)
  - CSS Files: Budgets + Logical Frameworks sample, 2012 (Box 212)
  - CSS Files: "Double Bind" NYC Launch, 2013-03-01 (Box 212)
  - CSS Files: International Human Rights Funders Group Conference, 2013-07 (Box 212)
  - CSS contracts and executive decisions, 2012 (Box 212)
  - CSS lawyers, 2011-2012 (Box 212)
  - Oak Foundation, 2012 (Box 212)
  - Urgent Action Fund for Women's Human Rights, 2006 (Box 212)
  - Dress Codes for fundraising project for CSS, 2012 (Box 212)
  - Freedom Network Conference, 2016-04-04-05 (Box 212)
  - Marc Fink (donor to the CSS), 2013 (Box 212)
  - CSS Files: International Human Rights Funders Group Conference meeting with Felice, 2013 (Box 212)
  - CSS miscellaneous notes, 2013 (Box 212)
  - Looking Forward Program, 2012-03-30 (Box 212)
  - Jacob Blaustein Institute (JBI) Conference on UN High Commission on Human Rights, 2012-02 (Box 212)
  - Code Pink debate, 2012 (Box 212)
  - Blaustein Report, 2012 (Box 212)
  - Gita Sahgal meetings, writings, etc., 2010; 6 folders (Box 212)
  - Chetan Bhatt writings, 2004-2009 (Box 212)
  - SSRC Literature, 2011-2012 (Box 212)
  - Center for Constitutional Rights (CCR) publication, 2012 (Box 212)
  - CCR Albisa Case, 2010 (Box 212)
  - AWID Fundamentalism paper, 2010 (Box 212)
  - Karima Bennoune writings, 2005-2009 (Box 212)
  - AWID International Forum of Women's Rights and Development List of Participants, 2005 (Box 212)
  - CSS London Meeting, 2011 (Box 212)
  - North American Rojava Alliance notes, n.d. (Box 212)
  - CSS 501(3) (c) forms, 2014 (Box 212)
  - Draft "Women's Rights in the Triangle of State, Law, and Religion" (Box 212)
  - Radcliffe Institute Conference "Gender, Sex, and Socialism", 2012-10 (Box 212)
  - CSS notes, 2011-2013; 5 folders (Box 212)
  - Rhonda Copeland's Estate gift to CSS, 2011 (Box 212)
  - Will and End of Life Directives, 2005; 2 folders (Box 212)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Restricted
  - Reading list for Ruth Walthins by Meredith Tax, 1962 (Box 212)
  - Publications on gender, 2009, 2013-2014 (Box 212)
  - A Road Unforeseen first draft, 2015; 3 folders (Box 212)
  - A Road Unforeseen second draft, 2015-11-25; 4 folders (Box 213)
  - A Road Unforeseen third draft, 2015; 5 folders (Box 213)
  - A Road Unforeseen final draft, 2016-03; 4 folders (Box 213)
  - A Road Unforeseen final draft and edits, 2016-04; 4 folders (Box 213)
  - A Road Unforeseen maps, edits, and images, 2015-2016 (Box 213)
  - A Road Unforeseen reader's notes, n.d. (Box 213)
  - Interviews and press about A Road Unforeseen, 2016 (Box 213)
  - Published copies of A Road Unforeseen, 2016; 3 folders (Box 213)
    English, Polish, and German translations.
  - Seminar on Women, Writing, and Power speech, 2008 (Box 213)
  - Correspondence, 2004-2006 (Box 213)